this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software
welcome to se radio my name is Johannes
and I'm here with Ken Kelly and I was
read to the biography of him Kenneth's
author of Adjara analytics a value
driven approach to business intelligence
and data warehousing he is a pioneer in
combining agile methods with data
warehousing business intelligence
analytics ken has written extensively
about agile analytics for the cutter
consortium zoom and his block the agile
is calm so welcome to the show Ken thank
you is there anything you want to add to
your biography no except that I am the
director of advanced analytics
forethought works and we have data
science team teams all over the world
working on analytics so so can you start
with explaining maybe what analytics
means in one minute or so sure so so
analytics is of is a very large umbrella
term it ranges from descriptive
analytics most companies have business
intelligence reporting dashboards sort
of it's sort of like looking in the
rearview mirror finding out what has
happened then we move into predictive
analytics using techniques like data
mining statistical analysis machine
learning for anticipating or
probabilistically predicting what might
happen or what what is likely to happen
and then at the at the far end of the
spectrum is prescriptive analytics where
we can actually use analytics as a way
to influence shopping behaviors or
operational behaviors or things to
happen so that's so analytics kind of
runs the spectrum from business
intelligence to what we now call data
science which includes machine learning
data mining and statistics so what would
a typical analytics project look like
can you give a plastic example sure
actually there's a couple of different
examples the the most interesting
projects are projects where analytics is
part of a bigger solution so for example
I'll use something that Amazon is
amazon.com is working on in in North
America and I suspect this is going to
be true in the rest of the world it
costs a lot of money for Amazon to ship
items across the country America is a
very large country and it costs a lot to
ship from one coast to the other so
they're using data science and
predictive analytics to anticipate what
you might order what you based on your
browsing based on your past orders past
shopping similar to the way that Amazon
recommends items that might interest you
now what they're moving into is the
ability to predict ahead of time when
you're going to order something and they
use that to ship the item closer to you
not to your doorstep but they ship it to
a hub near you so that when you do order
it they can get it to you very quickly
without a lot of extra cost so that's
called anticipatory shipping and so the
project itself would include a lot of
data science to figure out how to make
those predictions and and when to take
action on those predictions and then the
bigger solution is the the problem of
moving items and and deciding when when
to to move the items near you so can you
elaborate a little bit on how they
actually find out that you might be
interested in it
sure so so there's there are several
techniques
that are used for these kinds of things
for recommendations systems we often use
a technique called collaborative
filtering one Tet one use of that
technique is to look at the
characteristics of the shopper so let's
think about yo.hannes characteristics
your age things that you've bought in
the past what you like to do lots of
information about you and find we can
look for other people that have similar
characteristics and we can say these
other people have purchased these items
therefore you might like this item as
well that's called collaborative
filtering from a shopper to a shopper
item by item means you if you're
browsing a book on on Amazon or you're
browsing an item in the store we can
look and see what so people who bought
that item also bought other items what
kinds of items did they buy that are in
common and that that can lead to
recommendations as well so that was a
recommendations scenario for for that
anticipatory shipping what we do is we
look at the data at the past data of
your behavior when you ordered things
maybe it's something like you browsed
one day and on average four days later
you you order the items so maybe there's
a pattern that can be uncovered through
multiple searches on the website that's
I'm I don't work for Amazon so I don't
know exactly what they're doing but
that's the sort of thing that we would
do to do that kind of prediction so each
each problem we apply a different
algorithm but what's I think what's
fundamentally different with analytics
from programming other solutions is that
instead of using a rules-based system a
series of if-then kinds of rules to make
a decision we use a fuzzy matching
or a probabilistic reasoning based on a
load of past data we're detecting
patterns in the data that support high
likelihood or a high probability of
something like that occurring again um
another example of this is credit fraud
detection so when shoppers use their
credit card the credit card company
knows what your behavior your normal
behavior is and if your credit cards
action looks unusual compared to what
you normally do it might get flagged as
a as likely somebody stole your credit
card so that's another use of predictive
analytics and it's all based on large
volumes of data yeah you mentioned data
science a couple of time I've heard the
term data scientists as well so what is
data science and what does a data
scientist do in his daily life yeah this
is a good question so so date the term
data science is a relatively new term or
at least it's become popular only in the
last two or three years the the phrase
the term was coined to describe somebody
who goes beyond statistics and
probability often we find data
scientists in the hard sciences so that
thought works our team of data science
in North America our PhDs in physics and
chemistry and and the sciences where the
what they have learned are a set of
skills for collecting massive amounts of
data so for example one of the data
scientists that I work with is he's an
astrophysicist so he's familiar with
collecting large volumes of data about
space stars and galaxies information and
analyzing that to possibly look for
detecting black holes or look for new
planets that sort of thing so so data
scientists they have strong statistical
analysis skills
but they also know how to program they
know how to manipulate data into a
format that's my noble or discoverable
they so they they have a spectrum of
skills that go beyond just statistics
they also know about machine learning
which actually comes from the computing
Sciences so so they kind of blend
together mathematics computing science
computational sciences the ability to
rigorously apply scientific method so
hypothesis testing and experimentation
all of these things come together to
create this role called data science and
what we're seeing I don't know if this I
don't know how how much this is true in
Europe but what we're seeing in North
America are more and more universities
are starting to offer degree programs in
data science or analytics and they tend
to be multidisciplinary so they don't
they don't it's not just in computer
science it's not just in research
sciences or mathematics it's a blend of
all of these things and so that's so
data scientists it kind of describes a
very special mix of skills but when I
look at it those people are more
therefore like the conceptual side of
formulating hypothesis and then like
feeding it into into the systems are
those people also program us or do they
realize do they have people who realize
this for them you know they so a good
data scientist will write their they'll
do their own programming and most data
scientists today are using languages
like R or Python they're you know MATLAB
is a popular programming environment SAS
SAS is those are two those last two are
commercial tools whereas R and Python
are open lane free languages having said
that data scientists aren't typically I
wouldn't call them software devs with
all the discipline and and practices
that good software developers use so to
some extent there
hackers we often at ThoughtWorks we
often try to pair a data scientist with
a dev so that the quality of the code
that they write goes up so it's not so
the data science the the role of the
data scientist is to take a business
question or it could be a business
question it could be a question from
some other domain but it's some
practical question like as an example if
I'm running a grocery store and I and I
offer a coupon for 20% off of peanut
butter I might lose money on that but
can I can I predict when people will
continue to buy peanut butter because I
gave them that very first coupon so
that's the business question can should
I invest in giving these coupons for
four items and what kind of what can I
expect what kind of behavior can I
expect after that so that's the business
question and the data scientist has the
ability to say I can turn that into an
experiment and I can use all of this
data to analyze who is likely to use
that coupon and then continue buying
peanut butter at full price after after
the fact so I don't know if that example
made sense but that's the data scientist
sort of takes the business question and
turns it into the research question and
then they write the program they write
the code to do that now in the example
of the Amazon the example I used earlier
of what they call anticipate or a
shipping the data scientists the the the
business leaders who have the idea of
saving money by by shipping items before
they've been ordered that's the big idea
and then the data scientists they're
their role is to say alright well how
can I collect all the data that I need
to make good highly relatively accurate
predictions to go ahead and do that
shipping and so the data science work is
a component of
bigger that bigger solution so he's he
is not only responsible for like
analyzing the data Wednesday when
they're there he's also responsible for
like having ideas of finding out which
kind of data I shouldn't actually gather
to make a prediction yes yeah that's
exactly right and so so the data a good
data scientist needs to not only have
those good analytical skills they need
to have some domain knowledge they need
to understand the the data that there
were how to interpret the data how to
manipulate the data so there's a lot
there's in fact we often say that about
80 percent of of data science is really
spent just wrangling data just just
getting getting the data into a format
that's ready to be analyzed in mind and
and modeled and so there's really a lot
of work preparatory work before you
start making the predictions so this
this this is something like you would do
with a data warehouse capturing the data
and bringing them into a form to
generalize them yeah very possibly so
data warehousing is interesting the
purpose behind data warehousing
is to pull information out of your
operational and transactional systems
into a format for analysis now most data
warehouses most conventional data
warehouses that have been built over the
last 20 years have generally been for
the purpose of doing business
intelligence reporting and and executive
dashboards or dashboard presentation of
data so often the data is structured in
a way that lets people drill down to low
levels of detail or aggregate up so it's
sort of examining and exploring the data
but but a data warehouse could also
serve up data that is prepped in a
different structure for this kind of
data science work that we've been
talking about
it's it's kind of interesting that
umbrella term analytics that we talked
about earlier there's there's a lot
happening in their data science and
business intelligence are two very
different sets of skills so bi
developers that you that build in tools
like MicroStrategy or Business Objects
are not the same people that are doing
data science work and building these
predictive models maybe you can
elaborate a little bit on what business
intelligent actually means sure yeah so
business intelligence is a field that's
been around for now for 25 years or so
the goal of business intelligence is to
give data-driven decision support to
executives and business leaders who need
to make decisions so it could be
financial data for making for analyzing
and forecasting the few you know the
next year of business or the next
quarter it might be human resources data
to make sure that you've hired the right
people and they're and they're they're
performing well it could be
transactional data to see when you need
to
I'll stick with with retail as an
example many retailers use business
intelligence as a way to know when peak
sales happen so they can stop staff the
stores or stock the stores appropriately
so that's so business intelligence is
generally that descriptive or rearview
mirror facing analysis that I talked
about earlier data science on the other
hand is more in the predictive and
prescriptive end of that range and it's
the skill set that we've been talking
about with people programming in R or
Python doing experimentation and
research so very different skills very
different tools and techniques still
fits within that so so business
intelligence is rather about
preventing the date or an easier
consumable form and analytics is like
deducing stuff from that's exactly right
that's a good way to say that and
there's a there's a term an acronym that
we use a lot in business intelligence
called OLAP online analytical processing
and and what a lot of data warehouses do
is they structure the data for online
analytical processing and what that
means is that the data can be it can be
sliced it can be you can take subsets of
the data easily you can filter the data
easily you can drill down to low levels
of detail like individual transactions
and customers or you can roll up the
data to a store level or city level
groupings of aggregates of the data so
that's business intelligence revolves a
lot around that sort of ability to drill
and slice and dice the data so with data
warehousing comes this notion of a
extract transform load mechanism ETL you
see it everywhere yeah what is it and
how much does it play into into the work
of a data scientists okay that's
interesting so ETL is the in the data
warehouse world is the bulk of the
programming it's usually done using it a
tool tools like informatica ab initio
there's some open source or semi open
source tools like kettle which is part
of Pentaho I won't rattle off all the
names but these are tools that enable
the ETL developers to extract data out
of the source databases so the
transactional systems or operational
systems transform the data into the
structures that it needs to be in and
load that data into the warehouse so
that's you can think of those steps as
being the the processing steps in order
needed in order to populate the data
warehouse
the challenge with ETL if you look at
large expensive data warehousing
projects the largest component or at
least one of the most expensive
components of data warehousing projects
is ETL creating the ETL testing it
making sure it's working properly and
then ongoing maintenance and support of
ETL is quite expensive one of the things
that I've been talking a lot about
lately is ingesting data differently so
so the traditional way of ingesting data
into a warehouse is doing that
extraction into an integration layer in
the in a multi layer architecture doing
your transformation and business logic
to to enhance and restructure the data
and then loading it into the warehouse
and so therefore there's a lot of
complexity that lives at that
integration layer in a in a multi in a
three-tiered data warehouse architecture
so something i've been talking about is
extracting data into a data core some
people are referring to this as a data
lake which is often using a no sequel
technology like Hadoop or something like
that simply grabbing the data moving it
into that that core or that Lake and
then only dipping data out as you need
it when you need it for the the
applications that need to be supported
so for example if you're going to
populate an executive dashboard you say
well what what data does that dashboard
need it's a subset of all of the data so
we'll just go grab just that data we'll
structure just that data for to support
the dashboard and then the workload is
smaller because you still have to do the
transformation but now you're doing
transformation on just that subset of
data so that the dashboard so that you'd
just have the data you need that's right
so you so the the the design principle
is just-in-time
only only take what you need when you
it and only transform what you need when
you need to transform it hmm
oh you had one other part of your
question that I didn't answer
you asked how how it's relevant to data
scientists data scientists ingest data
into there actually it's it's
interesting we talked about that slicing
and dicing in business intelligence data
science actually does something almost
opposite of that so typically in data
science what we do is we combine the
data into one flat wide table if you if
you think of it as structured column
data so we want big wide data with lots
of features or attributes and then the
table whereas a relational database has
lots of tables that are that are
connected to each other
data science uses it D normalizes that
data so ETL doesn't play a big role in
data science ETL plays a much bigger
role in data warehousing most data
scientists prefer to go straight to the
source or grab the raw untransformed
data into their data science feed so so
there's some different this this creates
an interesting challenge because data
warehouses are often designed to support
business intelligence and they have to
be rethought in order to support the
data scientists because it's a different
kind of thing yeah was I was thinking a
little bit is this along the lines isn't
like the transform of this ETL the job
of a data scientist when you when you
look at it for you
there there is some transformation that
data scientists do so the transform let
me think of a good example here so for
business intelligence I was on a project
some time ago where we needed to
calculate gross profit net profit and
cost of sale those were three those were
three calculations or an
formations that we needed to do in the
warehouse there were others as well
those particular calculations were quite
complicated for the this this company
this was a company that sells streaming
video and they have to pay they have to
pay the studio a royalty fee there's a
lot of fees that move around when you
when you enable people to watch a movie
online or or on their TV so so the
calculations were quite complicated
those transformations needed to happen
in order for the business intelligence
tools to do their job now we also did
some data science work on that project
we did some predictive modeling and as
it turned out we didn't use we didn't
take advantage of those calculated those
are called calculated measures we didn't
take so much advantage or the data
scientists weren't so much involved in
that transformation logic they simply
use that data as as additional features
in the in the predictive analysis now
what data scientists will often do is
what's called feature engineering so in
the in the world of statistics and and
machine learning we talked about what we
call a target variable which is and my
credit fraud example the target variable
is whether a transaction is fraudulent
or not whether you know what's the
probability that it's fraudulent or not
so you could say yes or no or you could
say a percentage but it's one field and
the data that is the prediction now all
of the other fields that are used to
make that prediction are called features
so the more features we have to work
with the more likely we are to come up
with patterns that will make that make a
highly accurate or a higher degree of
accuracy
so feature engineering is sort of like
transformation it's where we're using
singular raw features and combining them
to create yet another feature and maybe
a
another so kind of like the calculation
of net profit where we used raw data to
in a formula to create net profit a data
scientist might do something similar but
it's for a different purpose they don't
the data scientist doesn't create the
the business logic they just simply use
the the results of that does that make
sense yeah I'm wondering a little bit
about if you talk about multi multiple
features don't you run into the problems
of multiple testing problems where the
predictive value goes down because you
use too many information Oh so yeah this
is an interesting it this is a skill
that the data scientists have so not all
the features are meaningful in fact
there's a lot of noise and a little bit
of signal and so we're looking for the
signal in the midst of all that noise
and what we want is to find the features
that have the highest correlation to
make the prediction and we want to get
rid of the features that don't seem to
influence the the prediction so starting
with more features is good because
there's a likelihood of of getting
better predictability but it means that
you're carrying all those all those
features that aren't useful you're
carrying them along so what we do is we
start pruning we want to do feature
engineering to make good features and we
want to do pruning to get rid of
features that don't that aren't helpful
so there's this sort of it's sort of
part of the process of trimming down
your data set to be the features that
are the most meaningful and matter the
most going back a little bit but to data
warehousing I've heard that you promote
something called the agile processing
pipelines or some clients apparently
call it canvas truck can you elaborate a
little bit on there about what what this
actually is and why you think people
should consider it so this is actually
what I was describing earlier when I was
talking about the day
Lake or the more that's part of this
agile data processing pipeline so so my
argument is that conventional data
warehousing is it's too expensive and
it's prone to failure in my book I talk
about how you can use agile development
technique while still using a data
warehouse architecture that we've been
using for quite some time those
architectures aren't bad but they tend
to the conventional data warehouse
architecture tends to say let's extract
all of the data let's do a full source
discovery extract all the data into the
integration layer do apply all of the
transformation logic and then load that
data into the warehouse and most
conventional data warehousing projects
try to boil the ocean I don't know if
this is a term that's familiar in German
but maybe the the the the the metaphor
means trying to do everything all at one
time trying to grab all of the data
trying to figure out all of the
transformation logic the resolve on data
yeah big design up front it's very
similar to that so so that's a
fundamental problem and in my and so my
book says go ahead and use conventional
architectures but do it in an agile
iterative fashion pulling data a little
bit at a time all the way through your
architecture the agile data processing
pipeline that that one client has
started referring to as the Ken for
structure is it takes this a step
further it says now that we're doing
we're pulling just what we need when we
need it
let's move the transformation logic as
close to the business as possible so
that you you can pull data quickly
cheaply scalably into the lake or the or
the core and then you can dip out of
that core only what you need and then
apply the logic at that at that outer or
the final stage in the in the
architecture so I think of it I actually
have pictures of this that I draw
as concentric circles where the
innermost circle is the core you want to
ingest data into that core cheaply and
and easily so that you can just put data
in there and not have to think about how
it's going to be used and then the then
there's an information layer around the
core where the information layer is the
Publishing's it's a publish and
subscribe model that says we will dip
the data out of the core structure it in
the right format for its intended
purpose and then the application sits on
top of that information layer and you
might the information layer you might
have four or five different ways to
structure the data so you might use a
relational database for one purpose you
might use a graph database for another
purpose you might use a column family or
another no sequel technology for and and
so each each of those data stores is
purpose-built and you can drive the
logic there instead of having a bunch of
transformation logic looming in the
middle so what mine a July Mari combined
agile development practices with this
agile processing pipeline and you've got
that that gives the team a lot more
ability to move quickly and adapt easily
hmm
when you when you will send me the this
thing I can put it in the show now okay
yeah I'll see that you said something
about its publish/subscribe mechanism
that means like the the transactional
data store is giving me information when
it stores data into it and I can react
to it yes
oh so that's that's actually I'm glad
you asked that because another
characteristic of this agile data
processing pipeline is that instead of
doing what so conventional data
warehouses pull data they go.they the
code reaches into the source databases
and pulls the data in usually on a
nightly batch basis what the what this
processing pipeline does is it is drip
feeds
the core by instrumenting those source
systems to send messages to put messages
on message bus or you can use other
techniques there's a technology that is
often used with Hadoop called Kafka and
it's a it's a sort of messaging type
system or you can use a you know pub/sub
technique as well but the idea being
that instead of doing nightly batch
movement of data you're just as data
arrives in the transactional system it
just immediately gets published on to
the message queue and where it can get
consumed by the data core and by any
other systems in contrast to the data
warehousing from a traditional sense you
have a more immediate feedback on your
data viewing application you have the
ability to do what's fairly close to
real-time analytics if there's a need
for that at the very least even if you
don't need real-time analytics what this
technique does for you is that it it
reduces how heavyweight the ETL
processes are so in fact virtually ETL
as a bunch of code goes away because the
e part the extract part is is now it's
ingestion through pub/sub the
transformation part lives in that
information layer that we talked about
so T the e and the T or the e goes away
the T is separated and the load happens
through that message Q out between the
core and the information layer I don't
know if this is making sense verbally
but the idea is that I'm trying to
eliminate that expensive ETL coding that
is a problem and mmm and that you only
do once for that's right yeah yeah okay
so you talked a lot about the like the
data you want to analyze and I was
wondering
why is it becoming more relevant now why
are we coming up with these things now
does it have to do something which the
buzzword big data well so so I think in
some sense it does so I started my
career in this field in early 1990s 91
or so my my PhD and my master's degree
both included artificial intelligence
and machine learning I got involved in
data mining which was very popular and
well I should say data mining was a hot
topic kind of like big data is data
mining was a hot topic in the mid 90s
the problem was that companies couldn't
get a hold of their data to mine it so
they all liked the idea but they they
didn't have they didn't have their data
and well-managed so that became so data
warehousing became a big deal because
companies realized that they would like
to mine their data but they couldn't do
it so now flash forward 20 years we now
have these new technologies these Big
Data technologies like Hadoop and
Cassandra and a variety of others and
many of the the relational database
vendors now have new technologies as
well in memory databases etc all of
these things have given rise to a whole
new opportunity to analyze large volumes
of data that we couldn't do 20 years ago
so I think that the there's a couple of
things
Big Data has become a overused buzzword
it's unfortunate it's it's also often
assumed that Big Data also means data
science those two don't have to you can
have big data management without doing
any data science what does big data mean
actually big data I think that the so
the term was actually coined in 2004
it was described in a Gartner and
analysis Doug Laney as the like I don't
think Doug Laney coined the term but
Doug Laney of Gartner described big data
using what are commonly known as the
three V's volume velocity and variety
big data has large volume so it's it's
we now have the ability to store and
analyze much larger volumes of data than
we've been able to reasonably manipulate
in the past big data has high velocity
it's coming at us very fast
it also decays very fast so we might
think of like a Twitter the firehose of
Twitter data it's it's relevant for a
short time but it's a lot of data if you
want to analyze Twitter data and then
it's got a lot of variety so now we have
the ability to have we can analyze video
we can do facial recognition we can use
we can have audio we can have text so it
doesn't all have to be relationally
structured it's got this wide variety of
formats and structures and we can bring
all that together so so a lot of things
the you know the use of audio data
combined with metadata about the audio
file combined with an image we can
combine all of this and do really
interesting data science not always good
it's like like used I know that the
American the NSA has been in the news a
lot for using analytics for very scary
purposes that's unfortunate because we
with it's it's sort of with power comes
responsibility and and it's questionable
whether that's very responsible but
anyway I got trapped there yeah all
right so when this big data is like the
thing coming up
does it create the momentum for what we
call analytics these days it's it's made
data science be a lot more possible and
achievable for companies there are three
or four types of companies there are
companies for which data science is
central to what they do so companies
like eBay Facebook Amazon without
analytics they would not be nearly as
successful as they are I met I I know
the analytics director at eBay and he
made an interesting comment to me he
said eBay doesn't make anything they
don't buy anything and they don't sell
anything they just provide a platform
for people to sell things to each other
so all they have is data to make their
business and to make the experience for
their customers better so data is
central to what they do so there's that
first kind of company is the company
that that they know that that data and
analysis or data science is central to
what they do second kind of company is a
company that they recognize that they
have that there's value in the data and
they are looking for ways to create that
value from the stored data but they
don't see data as being central to their
business and their existence so many
traditional retail chains might fall
into this category they these are you
know companies that have gotten by fine
for years on intuition and experience
they they know that they can benefit
from data science or data analysis but
it's not you know they can still get
along without it and the third type of
company are companies that have data but
they're there they don't realize that
there's potential value and that hidden
in that data
I often talked to clients and companies
about whether their data is truly an
asset or whether it's a liability and my
argument is that that if you're in a
company where all the data are
being collected and stored but nothing
is there it's not being used for
anything then it's taking up space it's
taking up people time to manage it it's
an it's a liability it's expensive
whereas the companies that do a good job
of analyzing and enhancing their data
they're turning that into an a true
asset and and so I encourage companies
to consider how to make their data as
much as valuable an asset as possible
let's change topic a bit um why is it
agile analytics so analytics by nature
is not inherently agile so what what
would you define as agile so agile is is
the ability to deliver to create and
deliver value early and frequently in a
project so whether it's a software
project let's start with software since
that's where the agile movement came
from in in the world of software there
are some people some companies or
project teams that work in a what's
called a waterfall fashion which is
design everything upfront do the
requirements analysis do the design up
front build and build and build do tail
end testing and then deliver the
solution all in one Big Bang at the end
those projects commonly fail they they
fail to meet the true requirements or
they fail to deliver the the exit meet
the expectations of the the the
customers the end users so now what I've
done with my book is to take agile
software techniques and apply them to
analytics it's not a big leap except
that the the world of data the community
of people that are that are working with
data data warehousing business
intelligence data science they're not
the same people that are building
software so they haven't heard the
software message and even if they have
they have they haven't done a good job
of understanding how these things and
software can apply to
to their right yeah so so the you know
simply put the agile agile techniques
are typically fast iterative cycles of
development where we do a little bit of
requirements a little bit of design a
little bit of build a little bit of
tests and we quickly showcase that
working those working features to the
the stakeholders and we elicit their
feedback we want to know how they do
they like it do they accept it do you
know how do we adapt to that feedback
and in that process and so this is you
know every week to two weeks we're
delivering new working features in the
case of analytics we're delivering new
either predictive models or new
discoveries or new insights that
business stakeholders can evaluate they
can say this is useful I can take action
on this I know what to do with this or
they can say can you go back and do a
little bit more do something a little
bit different so same concept every week
or two we're trying to provide something
of value meanwhile we're continuing to
iterate on the analysis so you know you
might a conventional data science
project might run three to six months
before it produces you know good
accurate predictive models agile agile
data science or agile analytics we would
produce an early predictive model it
might not be really as accurate as it
could be meaning maybe it's better than
flipping a coin but not by much so think
my credit fraud example it might be an
early predictive model that kind of
predicts credit fraud but it misses a
lot of the time and then we iterate on
that and iterate on that
so we're incremental II making the
accuracy better but we're also getting
feedback from the business to make sure
we're doing the right thing and and
using the right approaches so how do you
achieve this so because you said not all
projects work this way why is that so
sounds obvious when they tell us doesn't
it so so the first problem is that the
agile movement in software blew up
around 2001 actually it 2001 was when
the agile alliance was formed and the
agile manifesto was signed that was the
core group of 17 people Martin Fowler
who's another thought worker with
another show guest from some episodes
ago yes ok so another part another so
the the movement started into started a
little bit before this but 2001 it kind
of consolidated by about 2004 the
software community was really starting
to pay attention meaning that companies
like banks and insurance companies we're
starting to say hey this looks like a
good way a better way to develop
software the problem is that the data
community didn't start paying attention
until about 2009 or 10 I started writing
about this in 2004 about using agile for
data warehousing in 2004
my book came out in 2010 actually 2011
and I was first asked to speak at a
conference on this subject in 2010 and I
think I was the first if this was a data
warehousing Institute world conference
and I was the first keynote speaker to
have spoken about agile data warehousing
at that time and and it was a very new
concept to people in the data community
so the data community has lagged behind
software in this in picking up this
agile approach I think it's confusing
for a lot of people software is about
custom building functionality from raw
code or source code data management
business intelligence advanced analytics
is it's a different
it looks and feels different
so it takes some takes some abstraction
and generalization to think about how to
apply these these techniques so the
guiding principles are deliver value
collaborate frequently with your
stakeholders and and working software or
working analytics in our case is the
measure of success we can stick with
those values and we can adapt the
practices to work for data science but
it's new to a lot of people I think
that's the biggest problem and what kind
of practices do you employ so what I've
tried to do now this actually this
actually looks different in data science
than it does in data warehousing so for
ETL development in a data warehouse
environment and for data modeling in a
data warehouse environment I've done a
live what I've tried to do is take a lot
of the software practices and adapt them
to ETL development so things like
test-driven development
pair programming use of patterns
refactoring those those ideas all apply
to ETL coding but they're tricky to
apply because we're not writing like the
the data warehouse practitioners aren't
using languages like Java or Ruby or
other languages to write this ETL code
they're using a commercial software
package so figuring out how to test it
how to do unit level testing that's kind
of a new concept but those practices
pretty that conceptually they apply so
the things that the software community
software developers are doing applied to
ETL data science is a little different
so in data science what we do is we may
we may try out a dozen different models
or algorithms before we hit on one
that's going to start to produce some
good results so we may write a lot of
throwaway code
in the process of figuring out which
algorithmic technique or which which
models are going to become relevant so I
often describe this as a lab a lab phase
and a factory phase so the lab phase is
where we're we're doing we're hacking
code we're moving quickly we expect to
throw it of that code away and as soon
as an algorithm or an approach starts to
look like it's gonna be capable then we
need to transition into a factory
mindset where we need to put tests
around the code in the case of Python
it's there's unit test framework for
Python there's behavior driven
development for Python so so if you as
you transition from this lab mindset to
a factory mindset a data scientist
especially pairing with a good developer
can start to put tests around that code
they can their I don't know about
patterns usage quite as much but in like
I'll go back to my credit fraud
detection example what ultimately has to
happen for that to be a good model is
the model goes into production against
live streaming data so as soon as you
swipe your credit card or the vendor
swipes your credit card that transaction
goes over the wire it runs through this
analytical model which scores it and
says this looks like a fraudulent
transaction and it gives the vendor back
a message that says card declined and
and that happens like really fast so
that means that the predictive model got
built in the lab validated and verified
in the lab and then the developers
working with the data scientist had to
actually write production code or turn
that code into production quality code
and put it into into action in that case
the agility starts it starts as you
transition from the lab into the factory
and then it's just it's like software
development
it's similar to Joseph a development
project exactly all right so as our time
is nearly up is there a question you
would have liked me to ask her is there
anything you want to say yes closing
words oh let's see
oh yes so the question that I think we
should all be asking is what is the
future of data science so so the the
interesting thing that we've been
talking about requires a lot of human
work expertise skills and time now we
are moving into a world where everything
produces data your car is loaded with
data your your mobile device is loaded
with data if you have a if you have a
Fitbit or a you know a biomedic ro or
whether they called a personal health a
wearable device those things create data
everything is creating data so what's so
the question is what does that look like
how can if if it takes months you know
weeks two months in order to produce
good data science results how can we
possibly deal with this explosion of
data in a meaningful way isn't it all
just going to pile up and and bottleneck
and so my prediction is my theory is
that we're going to move into a place
where we write algorithms that and
there's this is this has been done a
little bit but we'll we'll start using
more and more algorithms that will just
continuously try to build predictive
models automatically and and many of
these models will be junk they'll be
thrown away but the ones that start to
hit and then and start you know the the
the machine can be building doing the
the automated data science in the
background and as soon as it starts
creating a prediction that's worthy of
attention it can it can bubble that up
to maybe a human
a human expert to to evaluate so if we
if we think about big data as being
massively parallel computing to manage
data or to process data now imagine a
massively parallel data science
automated data science process so that
so that we're not just processing the
data we're actually doing predictive
model development like like in real time
round the clock some models live some
models don't live I think it's kind of
fascinating I don't know exactly what
that looks like
but yeah I guess yeah I'll add one more
thing and you can edit this however you
see fit the the other question you
didn't ask and we didn't get into is the
ethics and morality of all of this so
usually this discussion of data science
is also triggers questions about the
ethical use of personal data medical
data I know in Germany you have very
strict laws and regulations around how
data can be used the rest of the world
doesn't have that including America and
it's a big problem
how if if a company is using its
customers data irresponsibly customers
will cry foul very quickly and and and
the company will lose customers the
government agencies they somewhat are
the same way except they're less
responsive to the people saying you know
you can't do this so in my country we
unfortunately have used 911 the events
of 911 as an excuse to give our
government permission to use our data in
less controlled ways and it's scary to
me and I and I think that that one of
the things that we need to establish
globally are some rigorous standards
and rules and guidelines for how data
can be used and cannot be used so
especially as its it's all statistics
and therefore it can be wrong that's
what's what the software predicts about
you that's exactly right it can be wrong
it can be it can be used to profile
people in ways that are that are not the
you know it could be it could be
detrimental so that's yeah there's a
there's a potential to misuse data
science and as much as I love this field
we have to be very responsible so that's
the that's the other question that I'm
asked all right how can people find out
more about all this agile analytics
you're doing so agile if you if you do a
Google search on agile analytics you
should find my website there are
starting to become more books available
in the subject one book that I've
recently gone through is a book called
agile data science it's it's quite good
it's it's actually a good example of
using Hadoop for to do agile data
science there is the the community that
are doing agile in data warehousing
business intelligence and data science
is it's growing slowly and it seems it's
it's you know there seems to be more and
more resources of coming available for
we will link to these in the show notes
as well so you don't have to type them
all right and how can people find out
more about you so you mentioned your
blog are you on Twitter or anything else
how can people get in contact with you
sure my my twitter handle is the agile s
th e AG IL IST my email address is Ken
Collier at the agile s comm ke n co ll
ier
and I have a website that's the agile is
calm so and I've I tried my best to put
use usable consumable information there
it's been a little while since I've
posted a blog there I need to do that
but you can contact me through that okay
perfect
any upcoming speeches let's see I'm
going to be yes as a matter of fact I'm
going to being in Copenhagen in early
September I'll be speaking at the
information it's called I am 2014
conference and I think if you go to I am
2014.07.19 find that on the TD WI
website okay perfect
then thanks very much you're welcome for
being on the show it was very
interesting I mentioned again the show
notes so all the stuff you mentioned
will be available so people don't have
to google and find out these things
extensively we would actually like to
have feedback how you liked the episode
as our listeners so either go to iTunes
or use our block to comment on us and
maybe tell us what you like the most and
what you liked the least about this
episode that's all for now goodbye
from SEO radio this is Janna speaking
bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SE -
radio net to support us you can
advertise su radio by clicking the de
crédit delicious or / buttons on the
site or by talking about this on
Facebook Twitter or your own blog if you
have feedback specific to an episode
please use the commenting feature on the
site so that other listeners can respond
to your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]